A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Washington, DC, Series O FA350
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Washington, DC, Series O
1940-1958, 1968-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
United States. Dept. of State. Bureau of Western Hemisphere Affairs
United States. President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization
United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs
United States. International Development Advisory Board
FA350
75.62 Cubic Feet 199 document boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 O
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The series is divided into eight subseries that reflect the individual appointments--with the exception of Subseries 5, which consolidates Rockefeller's three government reorganization committee appointments--plus one additional subseries that contains declassified documents from two of his appointments. The nine subseries are:
Subseries 1: Coordinator of Inter-American AffairsSubseries 2: Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic AffairsSubseries 3: Inter-American Development Commission and CorporationSubseries 4: International Development Advisory BoardSubseries 5A: Special Committee on Government Organization (SCOGO)Subseries 5B: Reorganization Advisory Committee (RAC)Subseries 5C: President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization (PACGO)Subseries 6: Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW)Subseries 7: Special Assistant to the President for Foreign AffairsSubseries 8: Presidential Mission to Latin AmericaSubseries 9: Declassified Materials
Scope and Contents note
This series is made up of Nelson A. Rockefeller's personal copies of correspondence, reports, and other documents gathered during his service in the federal government in ten presidential appointments between 1940 and 1969. All manner of documents can be found in these files, from handwritten notes to printed reports. Marginal notes found in Rockefeller's handwriting are not uncommon. These records both duplicate and complement official government records held in the National Archives and in presidential libraries.
Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); New York (State); New York (N.Y.); National security -- United States; Education; Economics; Economic policy; Developing countries; Civics; Civic improvement; Business enterprises, Foreign; Venezuela; State governments -- United States; United States; Public health -- Latin America; Social problems -- Latin America; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; International relations -- United States; Latin America; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Art, Primitive; Arts; Philanthropy; Brazil; Business; Federal government -- United States; Education -- Latin America; Agriculture; Agriculture -- Latin America; Philanthropy -- United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Government agencies; International relations; International economic relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966
- Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, August 1940-December 1944; 1; 32.8 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Following a 1939 tour of Latin America, Rockefeller sent a memorandum to President Franklin D. Roosevelt that expressed concern over Nazi influence in that region and recommended a program of U.S. cooperation and assistance to raise the standard of living in Latin America and to improve relations between the nations of the western hemisphere. President Roosevelt responded by appointing Rockefeller to head a new program that became the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs. Following the attack on Pearl Harbor in 1941, the agency coordinated the strategic defense of the region in the fields of information, economics, health, sanitation, agriculture, transportation, and culture and actively worked to frustrate Axis propaganda campaigns and economic designs on Latin America.
  This subseries includes 6 cubic feet of correspondence and 19 cubic feet of bound printed material such as reports, newsletters, circulars issued by the various divisions of the OCIAA, and a complete set of "En Guardia," a Spanish-language picture magazine about the war that was produced and distributed by the OCIAA. There are also 15 reels of microfilm containing office correspondence: 6 reels of abstracts of incoming correspondence and 9 reels of complete outgoing correspondence. This correspondence may duplicate some of that within the paper files, but it does include additional correspondence as well.
  Also found in this subseries are 61 motion picture films produced and distributed under the auspices of the OCIAA during the years 1940-1944. There is a substantial amount of documentation about the films in the papers of this series. These films appear to be NAR's personal copies. In 1942 the CIAA contracted with Walt Disney to produce 18 films, all of which exist at the Archive Center. The Julien Bryan films were produced for a primary and secondary level school audience. The films are in English or Spanish and address health, education, and cultural issues. The films are presented by the CIAA and are live-action in presentation unless otherwise noted.
  Moving Images
  - Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (CIAA)
    Biographical / Historical
    Under Nelson Rockefeller, the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs was created to support various health and social wellness initiatives, as well as to maintain cultural and commercial relations between North and South America. From 1940 to 1946, the CIAA used films and posters to advertise their projects in Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Haiti, Mexico, Peru, Uruguay, and Venezuela.
    Scope and Contents
    In 1942, the CIAA contracted Walt Disney Studios to produce 18 films, all of which are available at the RAC. An additional set of films produced by the Julien Bryan Studio created for a primary and secondary level school audience were not commissioned individually by the CIAA, but are included here because of their related content. Many of these films are in Spanish, and some are animated features, or a combination of animation and live-action.
    There is a substantial amount of documentation about these films in the Nelson Rockefeller papers. These reels, including the material produced by Walt Disney Productions, are thought to be Nelson Rockefeller's personal copies.
    Arrangement
    Alphabetical.
    Conditions Governing Access
    When requesting to view films -- please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1902).
    If the item does not have a designated AV number, please refer to the Title and the Film Number (which consists of a combination of Roman numerals and alphanumerics - example: III 14.1-6).
    - The Amazon Awakens, 1944; Sound, Color, 40 min. (Box 2, Dvd AV 1269, Reel AV 1269)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      All inquires to view films require advanced notice of at least 24 hours, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those not available in modern formats, may be restricted from scholarly access at the discretion of RAC.
      History and future of the Amazon Basin region. A Walt Disney Production.
    - Argentine Primer: A Talk by Julien Bryan, c. 1940s; Sound, Black and white, 23 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1270)
      Access copy available.
      Overview of urban and rural life, culture, industries, exports; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
    - Belo Horizonte, c. 1940s; Sound, Black and white, 17 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1271)
      Planned city expansion, Brazil: growth, industry, housing and institutions. Produced by the CIAA/ Office of Strategic Services.
    - Bolivia, c.1940s; Sound, Black and white, 20 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1272)
      Rubber industry, geography, mining, and agriculture in Bolivia. Narrated by Jose Ferrer, presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
    - Brazil, c.1940s; Sound/Silent, Color, 18 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1273)
      Footage of Rio, Sao Paulo, coffee production, and a poisonous snake ranch.
    - The Bridge, c.1940s; Sound, Black and white, 30 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1274)
      Overview of South American industry, economy, agriculture, and the underutilization of resources, with a look towards future development with the aid of air transportation. A Motion Picture by Willard Van Dyke and Ben Maddow. Presented by Documentary Films Production and the Foreign Policy Association along with the CIAA.
    - Colombia: Crossroads of the Americas, c.1940s; Sound, Black and white, 26 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1275)
      Overview of Colombian geography, history, agriculture, industry, culture, and politics; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
    - El Cuerpo Humano (The Human Body), 1944; Sound, Color, 9 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1276, Reel AV 1276)
      Animated feature about the components of the human body, and what is required to keep healthy; presented by Walt Disney Studios, as part of the "Health for the Americas" series.
    - El Cuidado del Nino (Infant Care), 1944; Sound, Color, 9 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1277, Reel AV 1277)
      Animated feature about the components of the human body and what is required to keep; presented by Walt Disney Studios as part of the "Health for Americas" series.
    - Defensa Contra La Invasion (Defense Against Invasion), 1944; Sound, Color, 12 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1278, Reel AV 1278)
      Animated feature about infection and the effectiveness of vaccines; presented by Walt Disney Studios.
    - Down Where North Begins, c.1940s; Sound, Color, 20 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1279)
      Tour of Ecuador: cities, villages, mountains, traditional activities like spinning wool, weaving, and hunting. Produced by Herbert Knapp Productions and narrated by Ben Grauer (not commissioned by the CIAA).
    - La Enfermedad se Propoga (How Disease Spreads), 1944; Sound, Color, 10 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1280, Reel AV 1280)
      Animated feature on polluted water, insects, and poor hygiene and sanitation; presented by Walt Disney Studios as part of the "Health for the Americas"
    - Es Facil Comer Bien (It is Easy to Eat Well), 1945; Sound, Color, 8 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1281, Reel AV 1281)
      Animated feature on the needs and benefits of a well-balanced diet, and how to create healthy meals at home; produced by Walt Disney Studios, as part of the "Health for the Americas" series.
    - Fundo in Chile, c.1940s; Sound, Black and white, 20 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1282)
      Film about life and agriculture on a large family estate; presented by Julien Bryan Productions
    - Good Neighbor Family, c.1940s; Sound, Black and white, 17 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1283)
      Urban and rural life throughout Latin America; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
    - Guadalajara, c.1940s; Sound, Color, 17 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1284)
      Tour of the city: architecture, art, pottery, seascapes; produced by the Mexican Tourism Department and narrated by Walter Abel.
    - The High Plain, c.1940s; Sound, Black and white, 19 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1285)
      Life of the Indians on a hacienda in Bolivia; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
    - La Historia de Jose (The Story of Jose), 1944; Sound, Color, 11 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1286, Reel AV 1286)
      Animated feature from Walt Disney Studios, part of the "Reading for the Americas" series (# 3).
    - La Historia de Ramon (The Story of Ramon), 1944; Sound, Color, 11 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1287, Reel AV 1287)
    - Housing in Chile, c.1940s; Sound, Black and white, 18 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1288)
      Story of a family working within the government's improved housing plan; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
    - El Imperio Inca (The Incan Empire), Sound, Color, 21 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1509)
      General note
      Spanish.
      Study of Incan ruins and architecture in present-day Cuzco, Peru
    - Inauguration of President Vargas (Brazil), 1951; Silent/sound, Black and white, 13 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1290)
      Newsreel footage of international leaders, including NAR, in ceremonial garb, with greeting in Portuguese from President Vargas
    - Insectos Que Transmitten Enfermedes (Insects that Transmit Diseases), 1945; Sound, Color, 8 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1291, Reel AV 1291)
      Animated feature about lice, mosquitoes, flies, and other harmful pests and their removal; presented by Walt Disney Studios
    - Inspection of Women's Service Units, 1951 March 3; Silent, Black and white, 9 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1292)
      Film of a visit of the Norfolk Naval Air Station, Langley Air Force Base, and WAC Base. Produced by the U.S. Department of Defense
    - Introduction to Haiti, c.1940s; Sound, Color, 15 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1289)
      Footage of Port Au Prince: the market, language, traditions, and politics of the people. Presented by Mary Darling Productions; narrated by Milton J. Cross
    - Jose Como Bien (Jose Eats Well), 1944; Sound, Color, 11 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1293, Reel AV 1293)
      Animated feature from Walt Disney Studios, part of the "Reading for the Americas" series (# 2).
    - Lima, c.1944; Sound, Black and white, 15 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1295)
      Life, health, art, and education in the urban center; presented by Julien Bryan Productions
    - Lima Family, c.1944; Sound, Black and white, 18 min.; 16mm film (Reel AV 1296)
      Life of an upper/middle class family in Peru; presented by Julien Bryan Productions.
    - La Limpieza Trae Buena Salud (Cleanliness Brings Good Health), 1944; Sound, Color, 8 min.; 16mm film (Box 2, Dvd AV 1297, Reel AV 1297)
      Spanish
      Animated feature comparing sanitary and unsanitary living conditions; produced by Walt Disney Studios as part of the "Health in the Americas" series.